Research Interests_

Privacy, Federated Learning & AutoML: My primary focus is on learning, designing and building privacy-preserving federated systems and automated learning systems. My current research interests include privacy-preserving Machine Learning, Federated Learning and AutoML. Some of my past interests include Wireless Communications (3G and 4G) and IoT.

Education

Purdue University W. Lafayette, IN

PhD in Electrical and Computer Engineering

Aug. 2018 - May 2023

Hyderabad, India

- Advised by Prof. Xiaojun Lin
- Major GPA: 3.6/4.0

Indian Institute of Technology, Hyderabad

B.Tech (with Honors) in Electrical Engineering

Aug. 2014 - May 2018

- · Advised by Prof. Bheemarjuna Reddy
- Major GPA: 8.88/10

Honors & Awards

2020	Graduate Research Assistantship, SuperPower Group, Psychological Sciences, Purdue	Indiana, USA
2017	Two-Year Graduate Teaching Assistantship, Electrical and Computer Engineering Department, Purdue	Indiana, U.S.A
2018	Winner and World Finalist for Emergensor Startup, Microsoft Imagine Cup, Japan National Final	Tokyo, Japan
2018	Winner, Third Business Plan Competition, University of Tokyo	Tokyo, Japan
2017	India-Japan Engineering Program Research Scholarship, University of Tokyo	Tokyo, Japan
2016	Undergraduate Teaching Assistantship, IIT Hyderabad	India
2016	Special Recognition & 8 th Rank for Young Team, IEEE Signal Processing Cup	India
2014	Academic Excellence Award, IIT Hyderabad	India
2010	Recipient of the prestigious National Talent Search Examination (N.T.S.E), Govt. of India	India

Publications

Ajinkya Mulay, Sean Lane, Erin Hennes "Private Hypothesis Testing for Social Sciences"

SuperPower Lab, Purdue

THEORY AND PRACTICE OF DIFFERENTIAL PRIVACY, ICML 2022

Ajinkya Mulay, Sean Lane, Erin Hennes "PowerGraph: Using neural networks and principal components to multivariate statistical power trade-offs"

SuperPower Lab, Purdue

Al for Science, ICML 2022

Rakshit Naidu, Harshita Diddee, Ajinkya Mulay, Aleti Vardhan, Krithika Ramesh, Ahmed Zamzam, "Towards Quantifying the Carbon Emissions of Differentially Private Machine Learning"

OpenMined

SOCIALLY RESPONSIBLE MACHINE LEARNING, ICML 2021

Ajinkya Mulay, Tushar Semwal, Ayush Agrawal, "FedPerf: A Practitioners' Guide to Performance of Federated Learning Algorithms"

OpenMined

NEURIPS 2020 PRE-REGISTRATION EXPERIMENT WORKSHOP

Ajinkya Mulay, Anand Basawade, Bheemarjuna Tamma, Anthony Franklin, "DFC: Dynamic UL-DL Frame Configuration for Improving Channel Access in eLAA"

NeWS Lab, IIT Hyderabad

IEEE NETWORKING LETTERS

Ajinkya Mulay, Hideya Ochiai, Hiroshi Esaki, "IoT WebSocket Connection Management Algorithm for Early Warning Earthquake Alert Applications"

Esaki Lab, University of Tokyo

ACM/IEEE UCC, AUSTIN, TX, USA

Konkimalla Chandra Prakash, et. al., "A Novel Electric Network Frequency Classification Algorithm and an Electrical Power Signal Measurement Circuit"

LFOVIA Group, IIT Hyderabad

IEEE SIGNAL PROCESSING CUP, 2016

Invited Talks

- 2022 How to promote open science under privacy, Psychological Sciences Department, Purdue University
- 2022 PowerGraph: Using neural networks and principal components to multivariate statistical power trade-offs, IMPS
- 2021 Graphing multivariate statistical power manifolds with Machine Learning, MCP Colloquium, Purdue University
- 2020 FedPerf: A Practitioners' Guide to Performance of Federated Learning Algorithms, NeurIPS Pre-Registration Workshop

Skills

Focus Topics: Differential Privacy, Federated Learning, Graph Algorithms, AutoML **Machine Learning** PyTorch, Tensorflow, Keras, Pytorch-Lightning, Scikit-Learn, PySyft

Programming Python, Cpp, R, Go, MATLAB, MEX

Mobile Swift, Dart, Flutter, XCode

DevOps AWS, Azure, Docker

Languages English (Proficient), Japanese (Basic), Hindi, Marathi

Experience

Meta Menlo Park, CA

SOFTWARE ENGINEERING INTERN

May 2022 - Aug 2022

- Designed and deployed a modular and fully configurable end-to-end production stack for Federated Semi-Supervised Learning (FSSL) tasks.
- Identified and benchmarked high computational overhead due to certain matrix operators (75% of the total cost); passed the knowledge to the right stakeholders for mitigation.
- Replicated performance benchmarks for Federated Systems using the newly developed production stack for popular SSL algorithms FixMatch and SimCLR with image datasets.
- Enabled fast privacy research exploration to explore differential privacy, NoPeek, and NLP tasks with the deployed production environment.
- Technology Stack: C++, Torchscript, Python, PyTorch

Facebook Menlo Park, CA

SOFTWARE ENGINEERING INTERN

May 2021 - Aug 2021

- Developed a fast and highly scalable differentially private machine learning algorithm which outperforms the state-of-the-art model's test performance by 15%.
- Implemented additional visualizations to improve gradient flow and easily debug larger machine learning runs.
- Technology Stack: Python, PyTorch

SuperPower Group, Purdue University

West Lafayette, IN, USA

MACHINE LEARNING TEAM LEAD

Aug. 2020 - Present

- Designed algorithms to examine effects of parameter uncertainty on statistical power and identify regions of robustness/reactivity in specified parameter values over a high-dimensional parameter space
- Reduced inference, training time and resource usage to under 10% of the baseline with feature engineering while maintaining majority of the
 predictive capabilities
- Technology Stack: Python, PyTorch, Matplotlib, Pandas, Weights and Biases, R, Jupyter Notebooks, Git

OpenMined Remote, USA

RESEARCH SCIENTIST

Mar. 2020 - Present

- Developing methods to characterize Private Federated Learning Systems and identify and track the performance of Federated Algorithms over varied environments with a single easy-to-use metric; proposal accepted at Pre-registration Workshop, NeurIPS 2020
- · Demonstrated top 5 Federated Machine Learning algorithms on 100+ virtual mobile devices with an accuracy of over 99% on LEAF datasets
- Technology Stack: PyTorch, Weights and Biases, PySyft, Matplotlib

Electrical and Computer Engineering, Purdue University

West Lafayette, IN, USA

GRADUATE TEACHING ASSISTANT

Aug. 2018 - Mar. 2020

Mentored 350+ undergraduate students and 15+ undergraduate teaching assistants to develop a strong fundamental understanding of electrical
engineering concepts

NeWS Lab at IIT HyderabadUndergraduate Student Researcher

Hyderabad, India

Aug. 2017 - Apr. 2018

• Designed and developed an algorithm to reduce interference between eLAA-WiFi networks by 40% using Game Theory techniques

• Technology Stack: MATLAB, Python

Emergensor (Startup), University of Tokyo

Tokyo, Japan

CHIEF SERVER ENGINEER

Jul. 2017 - Dec. 2018

- · Built and maintained the back-end for a mobile application used to notify people of local emergencies
- Reduced the map's refresh time by **60%** to improve user experience
- Technology Stack: Azure, Java, Google Maps API, Android Studio, Go, Python

Esaki Lab, University of Tokyo

Tokyo, Japan

RESEARCH INTERNSHIP May 2017 - Jul. 2017

· Slashed the packet drop rate over a 3G IoT-Cloud network by 99% by designing a dynamic ping-pong connection management algorithm

• Technology Stack: Go, Arduino, C

LFOVIA Group, IIT Hyderabad

Hyderabad, India

Undergraduate Student Researcher

May 2015 - Jul. 2016

Developed a povel Neural Network-based classification algorithm to predict location of an audio recording using the Electrical Network Fre-

Developed a novel Neural Network-based classification algorithm to predict location of an audio recording using the Electrical Network Frequency (ENF) signature embedded in the audio file; achieved an accuracy of over 85%

• Technology Stack: MATLAB, Python

Teaching and Mentoring

MENTORING STUDENTS FOR ANVIL Jan 2022 - May 2022

Mentoring Undergraduate Students for the Anvil's Co-Founder AI Matching Platform Development

Graduate Teaching Assistant for ECE 27000 Aug 2019 - May 2020

Teaching assistant for Introduction to Digital Design

Graduate Teaching Assistant for ECE 20002 Aug 2018 - May 2019

Teaching assistant for Electrical Engineering Fundamentals II

Open Source_

PIPELINEDP FOR OPENMINED AND GOOGLE | GITHUB LINK | WEBSITE

Developing the next generation of open-source tools for enterprise use

May 2022 - Present

Other Services

2022 **Reviewer**, Conference on Health, Inference, and Learning (CHIL)

2022 Volunteer, ICLR

Extra-Curricular

2020-21 Active Blogger, Topics- Machine Learning, Differential Privacy, MS/PhD Applications

2018-21 Active Member, HKN (Eta Kappa Nau), Purdue University

2020-21 Active Member, Startup Purdue, Co-Founded Happyou, a mental health SaaS startup

2014-18 Soccer Member, Varsity Team, Inter & Intra-Collegiate Events, IIT Hyderabad

2015-17 Head of Finance, ELAN, IIT Hyderabad's Techno-Cultural Fest, managed budget in excess of \$40K

2015-17 Events and Workshop Manager, Entrepreneurship Cell, IIT Hyderabad